Inventory of the Carl R. Gerber papers, 1962-1997
Hoover Institution Archives
Carl R. Gerber papers
1962-1997
1962-1971
2015C9
Hoover Institution Archives
4 manuscript boxes (1.7 linear feet)
Correspondence, memoranda, reports, printed matter, and photographs relating to the Atomic Energy Commission's Plowshare Program, which developed proposals for peaceful uses of nuclear explosions, including Project Gasbuggy plans for natural gas release.
Gerber, Carl R.
Access
The collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2014.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Carl Reading Gerber was born April 12, 1936 in Cleveland, Ohio. He graduated with a B.A. in chemistry from Oberlin College in 1958. Gerber’s summer employment included positions at the Lewis Laboratory of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA) in Cleveland, Ohio and the Eastman Kodak Company in Rochester, New York. He taught freshman chemistry part time at the University of Wisconsin, where he earned his M.A. in inorganic chemistry in 1960. From June 1960 to June 1961, Gerber worked as a technical intern at the Division of Technical Information (DTI) of the Oak Ridge National Laboratory in Oak Ridge, Tennessee, and he worked as Technical Editor of DTI’s Publications Branch from December 1960 to December 1961.
Gerber next worked for the Division of Peaceful Nuclear Explosives of the Atomic Energy Commission (AEC), where he was involved with the planning and gathering of technical information needed to successfully launch the Plowshare Program. He served as a Program Development Specialist engaged in research and the dissemination of program materials, and in 1969 Gerber became Assistant Director of the Division.
In later years, he continued to be involved with research related to energy and the environment, including serving as the U.S. representative on the Energy and Environment Group of the Organization of Economic Cooperation and Development.
Scope and Contents of Collection
Correspondence, memoranda, reports, and printed matter (such as supplements and brochures) relating to the Plowshare Program, which proposed peaceful uses of nuclear explosions, including Project Gasbuggy plans for natural gas release. These materials provide details about Plowshare experiments, complete with date, name, purpose, location, and research areas, such as: natural gas stimulation, engineering, peaceful explosions, excavation, underground engineering, seismic effects, and neutron physics. Other materials, such as symposium proceedings, illustrations, diagrams, communications, and photographs, are also included.
Nuclear energy--Industrial applications--United States.; Nuclear energy.; Nuclear excavation.; Project Plowshare (U.S.); Project Plowshare (U.S.)--Periodicals.; U.S. Atomic Energy Commission--Periodicals.
- Atomic Energy Comission (AEC) Correspondence, 1962-1972
  Scope and Contents note
  Letters to stakeholders, including United States government entities (such as the United States Congress) and private sector interests (such as the El Paso Natural Gas Company). Correspondence is related to the dissemination of information regarding the various Plowshare operations and the AEC's informational materials, which include transcripts of talks, project information sheets, proposals, and memoranda.
  - 1962-1963 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - 1964-1965 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - 1966 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - 1967 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - 1968 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - 1969 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - 1970 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - 1971 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - 1972 (Box-folder 2: 4)
- Atomic Energy Commission (AEC) and Plowshare Program Records, 1962-1995
  - Sections A - C, 1962-1995 (Box-folder 2: 5)
    [Bulk dates: 1963-1972]
    A) Carl R. Gerber personal files
    B) Glossary of Plowshare and related terms, December 1962; Plowshare chronology, July 31, 1971
    C) Annual reports
  - Section D, 1962-1995 (Box-folder 2: 6)
    [Bulk dates: 1962-1972]
    D) Technical information; fact sheets
  - Sections E - G, 1962-1995 (Box-folder 3: 1)
    E) Public information, general--press clipping, releases, brochures, booklets
    F) Critique of Final Report of the A-PICSC, April 1971
    G) GAC review, May 1972
  - Sections H - K, 1964-1995 (Box-folder 3: 2)
    [Bulk dates: 1964-1973]
    H) Congressional hearings, general
    I) Non-proliferation/disarmament
    J) Charges for nuclear explosives
    K) Publications/presentations:
    --Talk given to the New York section of the American Institute of Chemical Engineers, April 15, 1964
    --Engineering with Nuclear Explosives, Chemical Engineering, July 6, 1964
    --Industrial and scientific applications for nuclear explosives, BNES lecture, September 26, 1966
  - Sections L - P, 1962-1995 (Box-folder 3: 3)
    L) Briefings/remarks:
    --Remarks at Gasbuggy briefing, December 9, 1969
    --ANS and Southern Colorado State College talk outline, October 1969
    --“Nuclear Explosives as an Engineering Tool,” book chapter, 1988
    --Thirteen other outlines (1968-1972)
    M) Scientific uses
    N) Excavation
    O) Underground engineering uses, except Gasbuggy
    P) Gasbuggy, general
  - Sections Q - S, 1965-1995 (Box-folder 3: 4)
    [Bulk dates: 1965-1971]
    Q) Gasbuggy background/data sheets/etc.
    R) Gasbuggy press clippings, releases, speeches, etc.
    S) Gasbuggy project planning
  - Sections T - XYZ, 1967-1995 (Box-folder 3: 5)
    [Bulk dates: 1967-1968]
    T) Gasbuggy project operations
    U) Gasbuggy detonation day
    V) Gasbuggy related material
    W) Gasbuggy critique
    XYZ) [No materials follow this tab]
- Project Gasbuggy scrapbook, after 1967 (Box-folder 3: 6)
- Atomic Energy Commission (AEC) File, 1963-1997
  Bound printed materials, including selected annotated bibliographies for Peaceful Uses for Nuclear Explosives and Plowshare, published by the United States Atomic Energy Commission.
  - Peaceful Uses for Nuclear Explosives, 6th revision, annotated bibliography, circa 1963 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - Peaceful Uses for Nuclear Explosives, 7th revision, annotated bibliography, 1964 January (Box-folder 4: 2)
  - Peaceful Uses for Nuclear Explosives, 7th revision, supplement 1, annotated biliography, 1965 April (Box-folder 4: 3)
  - Plowshare, booklet, 1966 March (Box-folder 4: 4)
  - Plowshare, 8th revision, annotated bibliography, 1966 May (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - Plowshare, 8th revision, supplement, 1969 April (Box-folder 4: 6)
  - Plowshare: A Selected, Annotated Bibliography of the Civil, Industrial, and Scientific Uses for Nuclear Explosions, 9th revision, 1971 September (Box-folder 4: 7)
  - Nuclear explosives, printed materials, 1964-1997 (Box-folder 4: 8)